{
    "en": {
        "questions": [
            {
                "prompt": "How much plastic has been produced in 2017 (million tonnes)?",
                "options": [
                    "Less than 100",
                    "Between 200 e 300",
                    "Between 400 e 500",
                    "More than 500"
                ],
                "answer": 2,
                "description": "Worldwide plastic production has increased rapidly and steadily from the 60s up to now. In 2017 the total amount of plastic produced was more than 400 million tonnes, surpassing previous statistics.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "What is a polymer?",
                "options": [
                    "A set of giant molecules made up of smaller chains called repetitive units",
                    "A set of micro molecules that makes a big macromolecule",
                    "A set of repetitive units",
                    "A tiny molecule that attaches to another"
                ],
                "answer": 0,
                "description": "A polymer (word coined from the greek words “πολύς” and “μέφος”, translated many parts) is a set of giant molecules (macromolecules) made up of many smaller chains called repetitive units, kept together by covalent bonds.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "What are bioplastics?",
                "options": [
                    "There's no official definition",
                    "A plastic made at least partly of renewable resources or that is biodegradable",
                    "A biodegradable plastic",
                    "A plastic made of renewable resources"
                ],
                "answer": 0,
                "description": "There is not an official definition, but the definition approved the most (by European Bioplastic): “A material can be defined [a bioplastic] if it fulfills at least one of these characteristics: is made, at least partly, from renewable resources or it's biodegradable”.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Can plastic be made out of the peel of a banana?",
                "options": [
                    "Yes",
                    "No",
                    "There haven’t been any experiments regarding this",
                    "Scientists are still trying"
                ],
                "answer": 0,
                "description": "In 2013, at the age of 16, the student Elif Bilgin discovered the process through which plastic can be made out of a banana peel. For her discovery Elif won the first prize, consisting of 50 thousand dollars, at the contest “Scientific American Science in Action”.",
                "weight": 0.2
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Which continent produces the most bioplastic?",
                "options": [
                    "Europe",
                    "Asia",
                    "North America",
                    "Oceania"
                ],
                "answer": 1,
                "description": "The largest bioplastics producer in the world is Asia, which produces 55% of the worldwide production, followed by Europe which produces 19% of it, North America 16%, South America 9%, Oceania 1% and Africa, which doesn’t produce bioplastic at all. (statistics from 2018)",
                "weight": 0.3
            },
            {
                "prompt": "How much bioplastic is produced by industries in Italy?",
                "options": [
                    "117,000 tonnes",
                    "52,000 tonnes",
                    "73,000 tonnes",
                    "19,000 tonnes"
                ],
                "answer": 2,
                "description": "The main uses for bioplastics are the following: disposable shopping bags 68%, organic waste bags 13%, agricultural instruments, restaurants, food packaging and personal hygiene 19%.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "How much is the complete revenue of bioplastics industries in Italy (annual)?",
                "options": [
                    "Between 200 e 400 million euros",
                    "Between 450 e 600 million euros",
                    "Less than 200 million euros",
                    "More than 600 million euros"
                ],
                "answer": 1,
                "description": "In 2017 italian industries invoiced 545 million euros, with 2450 dedicated workers. (source Plastic Consult)",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "What is Ohoo?",
                "options": [
                    "An organization against non-recyclable plastics",
                    "A company that produces bioplastics from fruits and vegetables",
                    "A company that recycles bioplastics",
                    "A project that makes edible water bottles"
                ],
                "answer": 3,
                "description": "Three designers from London, Rodrigo Garcia, Pierre Paslier and Guillaume Couche won the Lexus Design Award for the invention of an edible water bottle made from a double layer in sodium alginate extracted from brown algae and sodium chloride.",
                "weight": 0.2
            },
            {
                "prompt": "If a polymer is made out of natural materials, is it always biodegradable?",
                "options": [
                    "No, it's never biodegradable",
                    "Yes, it's always biodegradable",
                    "Scientists haven't conducted any research about it",
                    "It depends from the chemical structure"
                ],
                "answer": 3,
                "description": "Plastics of type B, which are green plastics (bio-Pe, Bio-PP, Bio-PVC e bio-PET), are from renewable sources, but not biodegradable.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "How many types of bioplastics exist?",
                "options": [
                    "10 types and they're distinguished by grades of reuse",
                    "3 types: A, B, C",
                    "5 types: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5",
                    "There's only one type of bioplastic, vegetal"
                ],
                "answer": 1,
                "description": "There are three types of bioplastics, type A: polymers with a biological base from renewable sources and biodegradable; type B: polymers from renewable sources, but not biodegradable and type C: polymers from non renewable sources, but biodegradable.",
                "weight": 0.3
            }
        ],
        "lang": {
            "hintnotused": "Click for help, hints left %s",
            "hintsfinished": "You finished your hints",
            "hintused": "Hint already used, hints left %s",
            "questionindex": "Question %s",
            "descriptioncorrect": "Correct. Well done!",
            "descriptionwrong": "Wrong. You'll do better next time!",
            "nextquestion": "Next Question",
            "finish": "Finish",
            "resultaboveaverage": "Your score is above average, well done!",
            "resultunderaverage": "Your score is under average, try again?"
        }
    },
    "it": {
        "questions": [
            {
                "prompt": "Quanti milioni di tonnellate di plastica sono state prodotte nel 2017?",
                "options": [
                    "Meno di 100",
                    "Tra 200 e 300",
                    "Tra 400 e 500",
                    "Più di 500"
                ],
                "answer": 2,
                "description": "La produzione mondiale di plastica è aumentata rapidamente e regolarmente dagli anni ‘60 ad oggi. Nel 2017 la produzione di mondiale di plastica ha superato i 400 milioni di tonnellate, superando le statistiche precedenti.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Cos'è un polimero?",
                "options": [
                    "Un insieme di molecole giganti costituite da tanti mattoncini detti unità ripetitive",
                    "Un insieme di micro molecole che forma una grande macro molecola",
                    "Un insieme di unità ripetitive",
                    "Una micro molecola che si unisce ad un'altra"
                ],
                "answer": 0,
                "description": "Un polimero (parola coniata dall'unione delle parole greche “πολύς” e “μέφος”, tradotto molte parti) è un insieme di molecole giganti (macromolecole) costituite da tanti mattoncini detti unità ripetitive, tenute insieme da legami covalenti.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Cosa sono le bioplastiche?",
                "options": [
                    "Non c'è una definizione che vada bene per tutti gli studiosi",
                    "Una plastica che deriva anche solo in parte da risorse rinnovabili o è biodegradabile",
                    "Una plastica biodegradabile",
                    "Una plastica che proviene da fonti rinnovabili"
                ],
                "answer": 0,
                "description": "Non c'è una definizione che vada bene per tutti, ma la definizione più condivisa (dell'European Bioplastic): “Un materiale può essere definito [una bioplastica] se possiede almeno una di queste caratteristiche: deriva, anche solo in parte, da risorse rinnovabili o è biodegradabile.”",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Si può creare una plastica attraverso una buccia di banana?",
                "options": [
                    "Si",
                    "No",
                    "Non ci sono ancora esperimenti a riguardo",
                    "Gli studi sono ancora in corso"
                ],
                "answer": 0,
                "description": "Nel 2013, a 16 anni, la studentessa Elif Bilgin ha scoperto il processo con il quale creare plastica con la buccia delle banane. Per la sua scoperta la studentessa ha vinto il primo premio, ovvero 50 mila dollari, al concorso “Scientific American Science in Action”.",
                "weight": 0.2
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Qual è il continente che produce più bioplastiche?",
                "options": [
                    "Europa",
                    "Asia",
                    "Nord America",
                    "Oceania"
                ],
                "answer": 1,
                "description": "Il maggior produttore di bioplastiche al mondo è l’Asia, che produce il 55% della produzione mondiale, seguita dall’Europa che ne produce il 19%, l’America del Nord 16%, l’America del Sud 9%, l’Oceania 1% e l’Africa, che non ne produce affatto. (statistiche del 2018)",
                "weight": 0.3
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Quanti sono i polimeri lavorati dalle industrie delle bioplastiche in Italia?",
                "options": [
                    "117000 tonnellate",
                    "52000 tonnellate",
                    "73000 tonnellate",
                    "19000 tonnellate"
                ],
                "answer": 2,
                "description": "I settori applicativi prevalenti delle bioplastiche sono i seguenti: shopper monouso per la spesa 68%, sacchi per la raccolta della frazione organica 13%, strumenti agricoli, ristorazione, packaging alimentare ed igiene della persona 19%.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Quanto è il fatturato complessivo delle aziende di bioplastiche in Italia (annuale)?",
                "options": [
                    "Tra 200 e 400 milioni di euro",
                    "Tra 450 e 600 milioni di euro",
                    "Meno di 200 milioni di euro",
                    "Più di 600 milioni di euro"
                ],
                "answer": 1,
                "description": "Nel 2017 le industrie italiane hanno fatturato 545 milioni di euro, con 2450 addetti dedicati. (fonte Plastic Consult)",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Cos'è Ohoo?",
                "options": [
                    "Un'organizzazione contro le plastiche non riciclabili",
                    "Un'azienda che produce bioplastiche da frutta e verdura",
                    "Un'azienda che ricicla le bioplastiche in posate",
                    "Un progetto che crea una bottiglia d'acqua commestibile"
                ],
                "answer": 3,
                "description": "Tre designer di Londra, Rodrigo Garcia, Gonzalez, Pierre Paslier e Guillaume Couche hanno vinto il premio Lexus Design Award per l'invenzione di una bottiglia commestibile per l'acqua costituita da una doppia membrana in alginato di sodio ricavato dalle alghe brune e da cloruro di calcio.",
                "weight": 0.2
            },
            {
                "prompt": "È sempre biodegradabile un polimero ottenuto da fonti naturali?",
                "options": [
                    "No, non è mai biodegradabile",
                    "È sempre biodegradabile",
                    "Gli scienziati non hanno fatto ancora studi a riguardo",
                    "Dipende dalla struttura chimica"
                ],
                "answer": 3,
                "description": "Le plastiche di tipo B, ovvero le plastiche verdi (bio-Pe, Bio-PP, Bio-PVC e bio-PET), sono polimeri derivati da fonti rinnovabili, ma non biodegradabili.",
                "weight": 0.5
            },
            {
                "prompt": "Quanti tipi di bioplastiche esistono?",
                "options": [
                    "10 tipi e si distinguono per gradi di riutilizzo",
                    "3 tipi: A, B, C",
                    "5 tipi: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5",
                    "C'è solo un tipo di bioplastiche, quelle vegetali"
                ],
                "answer": 1,
                "description": "Le bioplastiche sono di 3 tipi: tipo A: polimeri derivati da fonti rinnovabili e biodegradabili; tipo B: polimeri derivati da fonti rinnovabili, ma non biodegradabili; tipo C: polimeri derivati da fonti non rinnovabili, ma biodegradabili.",
                "weight": 0.3
            }
        ],
        "lang": {
            "hintnotused": "Clicca per un aiuto, ne restano %s",
            "hintsfinished": "Hai finito i suggerimenti",
            "hintused": "Suggerimento già usato, ne restano %s",
            "questionindex": "Domanda %s",
            "descriptioncorrect": "Esatto. Ben fatto!",
            "descriptionwrong": "Sbagliato. Farai meglio la prossima volta!",
            "nextquestion": "Prossima Domanda",
            "finish": "Finisci",
            "resultaboveaverage": "Your score is above average, well done!",
            "resultunderaverage": "Your score is under average, try again?"
        }
    }
}
